Carlos Utrilla Guerrero

Institute of Data Science Paul-Henri Spaaklaan 1 The Netherlands E.MAIL

c.utrilla.guerrero@gmail.com

www:

https://carlosug.github.io/ ORCID:

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9994-1462

EDUCATION

University of Manchester, United Kingdom

2014

MSc in Social Research Methods & Statistics (CMIST)

Dissertation: Environmental Friendly Behavior and Sustainable food

Supervisor: Mark Tranmer

Other assignments: https://carlosug.github.io/posts/Social-research-methods-statistics

University of Southern Odense, Denmark

2012

MSc in Business Strategy & International Management (Erasmus)

University of Zaragoza, Spain (UNIZAR)

BA in Business & Administration

2011

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Knowledge graphs, open science, network science, semantic web, linked data, ontology engineering

CAREER PROFILE

PhD candidate, Research software engineer

COMPUTER SKILLS

Advanced: R and Python statistics and Machine Learning, Reproducible research and LaTeX

Intermediate: W3C Semantic technologies and ontologies (RDFS, OWL), NLP, GIS, HTML, CSS, Bash, SPARQL, SQL

Basic: REST API,D3.js visualization, Neo4J, MongoDB, Docker, Kubenetes

LANGUAGUES

Fluent in English, Basic level Dutch (A1), Intermediate level in French (B1-3) and Native proficiency in Spanish

WORK EXPERIENCE

Research Data Services, Delft University of Technology, the Netherlands

since November 2022

Research Data Scientist

Support the department in teaching and research activities in the field of data science and FAIR for software and data

Institute of Data Science, Maastricht University, the Netherlands

January 2020 - October 2022

Research Data Scientist

Supported the department in teaching, writing proposals/grants, and research activities in the field of data science, FAIR principles, semantic web and quantitative research methods

Develop linked data tools for researchers to use, and develop new methods for responsible data science practice

Kleos Space S.A, Luxembourg

August 2018 - December 2019

Data Scientist

Supported research group in need of data fusion and analysis using geospatial statistical and visualization methods European Space Agency (ESA) grant projects and proposals preparation, implementation and coordination

Kneip Communications, Luxembourg

2015 - 2018

Data Manager & Integration Officer

Participated in financial data analytics projects (involving data modelling and predictive analysis)

European Investment Bank, Luxembourg

2014

Financial Data Controller (6 months)

Budget preparation and control of EIB investment projects and related financial reports

Imaginarium Group S.A, Istanbul, Turkey

2013

Financial Data Controller Intern (7 months)

Built the financial and commercial Forecasting Model (leading the audit process and IT projects)

Young Aragoneses Entrepreneurs, Zaragoza, Spain

2011

Marketing Internship (6 months) Contributed to annual budgeting and report for association activities (International Business Plan)

Ibercaja Saving Bank, Zaragoza, Spain

Finance Internship (6 months)

2010

Explored Logistic Regression to calculate Probability of Default within SME portfolio and commercial loans

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

Turkiye I.S.I. Tme Engelliler Spor Federasyonu, Ankara, Turkey

2012

European Volunteer Service (7 months)

Collaborated in logistic and administrative activities and updated reports on local association activities

Partners ***	TITLE CV – PhD Candidate		
PROJECT ***	AUTHOR(S) Carlos Utrilla Guerrero	October 2022	PAGE 1 of 2
	•		

Current...... DSRI: Data Science Research Infrastructure (https://dsri.maastrichtuniversity.nl/) 2022 Supervisor: Michel Dumontier Activities: provide technical support for users and website documentation for computing and data science (https://api.dsri.maastrichtuniversity.nl/docs) Developing distributed analytics techniques (https://odissei-data.nl/en/privacy-preserving-techniques/) 2022 Activities: Implement preserving techniques for socioemotional data using semantic web standards and specifications PLAYFAIR: applying FAIR principles on digital humanities (https://qithub.com/MaastrichtU-IDS/play-fair) 2022 Co-authors: Michel Dumontier, Cameron Browne, Walter Crist Activities: Apply semantic web technology on historical games (e-data & research press article) KGFOOD: Distributed Knowledge Graphs CA19134 (https://github.com/MaastrichtU-IDS/kg-food) 2022 Co-authors: Remzi Celebi, Manuel Paneque Activities: Build a knowledge graphs on multilingual Food Composition Open Data (EU COST ACTION) Data Sharing Coalition (https://datasharingcoalition.eu) 2022 Activities: Participate in data sharing usecases (solid pods) with industry/research partners (press article) Past ESGREEN: Biodiversity Knowledge Graph (https://qithub.com/carlosuq/esgreen-kg) 2021 Co-authors: Michel Dumontier and Oscar Corcho Activities: Build a Knowledge Graph on biodiversity data using RDF and querying/analyzing with SPARQL CDDI: Community Data Driven Insight (https://carlosuq.qithub.io/posts/community-data-driven-insight) 2020 Service and Expertise Working Group Activities: Build data standards for different research projects within the university VHF maritime signals probability of transmission (https://carlosug.github.io/posts/GeolocationData) 2019 Kleos Space SA | European Space Agency (ESA) | Luxembourg Space Agency (LSA) Activities: Statistical analysis of different countries with geolocating dataset using MongoDB Query API TEACHNIG EXPERIENCE AND WORKSHOPS Courses Bachelor Global Studies BAGS (Quant. Research Methods Course - material) Semester IV 2022 Applied Research II VSK1004 (material) Semester VI 2022 Bachelor Global Studies BAGS (Quant. Research Methods Course - material) Semester I 2021

Applied Research II VSK1004 (<u>material</u>)	Semester VI 2021
Workshops, short courses and invited talks	
DARIAH-EU, Athens, Greece (<u>Conference Paper</u>)	June 2022
Metadata 4 DKE 2022, Lyon France (<i>COST EU</i>)	May 2022
PLAYFAIR, FAIR Coffee Lectures (<u>material</u>)	May 2022
Coding for researchers Python (University Library <u>material</u>)	March 2021
FAIR Essentials workshop (<u>material</u>)	February 2021
Online M-BIC Open Science Symposium (<i>Guest lecture</i>)	November 2020
R Carpentry Workshop (<u>Guest lecture eScience center</u>)	November 2020

Thesis supervision

New Science of Mental Disorders (*material*) February 2022 Mercedes Benz KG and FAIR data (proposal) March 2021

LIST OF JOURNAL/WEB PUBLICATIONS:

Co-founder of FAIR Coffee Lectures with Open Science Community Maastricht since 2021 1st In person DSRI Community Event June 2022

LIST OF JOURNAL/WEB PUBLICATIONS:

- Carlos Utrilla Guerrero, Vincent Emonet, Cameron Browne, Walter Chris and Michel Dumontier, "PLAYFAIR: Challenges and Solutions towards building FAIR database". In submission. ISW Special Issue Tools and Systems. 2022
- Carlos Utrilla Guerrero, Maria Vivas Romero, Marc Dolman and Michel Dumontier, "FAIR begins at home: Implementing FAIR via the Community Data Driven Insights". Accepted <u>FDO2022</u> Conference, October 2022
- Manuel Paneque, Carlos Utrilla Guerrero, M. Mar Roldan, Antonio Benitez-Hidalgo and Remzi Celebi, "KG for Food: towards a healthy dietary". In preparation <u>SWAT4LS</u> Conference, February 2023

SELECTED AWARDS

Research Fellowship grant in the national infrastructure 'CLARIAH Research Fellows 2021' (budget 15,000 euros)

Sports (football, tennis and padel official instructor, and swimming), travel and Human History

Partners ***	TITLE CV – PhD Candidate		JOB REFERENCE ***
PROJECT ***	AUTHOR(S) Carlos Utrilla Guerrero	ISSUED DATE October 2022	PAGE 2 of 2
	Carlos otrilla Guerrero	October 2022	2 01 2

ORGANIZATION Ontology Engineering Group (OEG)